RG 027, Board of Capitol Commissioners
Connecticut State Library
Board of Capitol Commissioners records
1871-1880
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Board of Capitol Commissioners
29 cubic feet
The Board of Capitol Commissioners oversaw construction of a new State Capitol building in Hartford.
RG027
1974-004
Historical Note
In July 1871 the General Assembly created a commission and authorized a bond issue and the expenditure of funds to plan and construct a new State Capitol building in Hartford. The old State House was to be turned over to the city.
The first Board of State House Commissioners accepted plans drawn by Richard M. Upjohn of New York and awarded a construction contract to James G. Batterson. In the middle of 1873 the General Assembly suspended the work and appointed a new commission to direct changes and improvements in the design and specification; as a result the building was made “fireproof”, it was considerably enlarged, and the planned modest clock-tower was replaced by the imposing gilded dome.
The building was completed and occupied in 1879.
Scope and Content
Includes minutes, correspondence, proceedings, contracts, proposals, specifications, estimates, plans and drawings, time books, materials lists and receipts, account books, vouchers, bank books and cancelled checks.
Related Material
In addition to the Upjohn drawings, the State Library has received various other manuscript items related to the construction of the Captiol. See the manuscripts and archives acatalog under Upjohn, R.M.; Batterson, James G.; and Connecticut. State Capitol.
, Connecticut State Library.
Index Terms
Persons:
Batterson, James G; Upjohn, Richard, 1802-1878
Organizations:
Connecticut. Board of Capitol Commissioners
Subjects:
Connecticut -- Capital and capitol; Connecticut State Capitol -- Hartford (Conn.); Connecticut. Board of Capitol Commissioners -- Records and correspondence; Hartford (Conn.). Buildings, structures, etc; Public buildings -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- Design and construction
Document Types:
Account books; Architectural drawings; Bank statements; Checks (bank checks); Check stubs; Contracts; Correspondence; Diaries; Minutes; Proceedings; Receipts; Vouchers
Restrictions on Access
See the policy.
Provenance
The Commission (which still sometimes called itself the State House Commission) turned over “the last of “ its files to the Comptroller on 30 November 1880, with an itemized list. Those records were transferred in March 1974 from Vault 2 in the Capitol basement to Archives in the State Library.
Container List
- Records, 1871-1880
  - 1. Minutes of meetings, 1871 August 25-1880 March 27; 3 volumes bound in 1 (Box Item 1)
  - Secretary's notes and drafts, 1872 Septemnber-1880 March (Box Box 2)
  - 2. "Important Memoranda", 1871-1880 (Box Box 3)
    Miscellaneous materials; included are freight receivpts, extra time books for office staff, notes on agreements with minor contractors, and some drafts of reports and of contracts.
  - 3. Letters received, 1871-1880
    - 1871-1876, 1 volume (Box Box 4)
    - 1877-1878 May, 1 volume (Box Box 5)
    - 1878 June-1879 August, 1 volume (Box Box 6)
    - 1879 September--1880 November, 1 volume (Box Box 7)
      Includes separate letters from James G. Batterson
    - Index to letters received, 1871-1877; 1 volume (Box Item 8)
    - Index to letters recieved, 1878-1880 (Box Item 9)
  - 4. Letters sent, 1872 March 7-1880-November 30
    - 1872-1876 September, 1 volume (Box Item 10)
    - 1876 October-1878 July, 1 volume (Box Item 11)
    - 1878 July-1879 October, 1 volume (Box Item 12)
    - 1879 October-1880 November, 1 volume (Box Item 13)
    - 1871 September-1877 May, 1 volume (Box Item 14)
    - 1877 May-1878 July, 1 volume (Box Item 15)
    - 1878 August-1879 July, 1 volume (Box Item 16)
    - 1879 August-1880 November, 1 volume (Box Item 17)
    - Index to letters sent, 1 volume (Box Item 18)
    - 1872 March-1877 May, 1 volume (Box Item 19)
      Duplicates.
    - 1877 May-1878 July, 1 volume (Box Item 19a)
  - 5. Record book, 1871 July-1878; 1 volume (Box Item 20)
    Transcriptions of legislation, resolutions, reports, contract, specifications, proposals and related correspondence, etc. Includes a table of contents.
  - 6. Diaries, 1871-1880
    - "Memoranda of Occurrences", 1 volume (Box Item 21)
    - E.P. McManus Journal, 1 volume (Box Item 22)
      Contains chronological notes of activities.
    - J.A. Brown's Journal, 1872-1873; 1 volume (Box Item 23)
  - 7. Dome investigation proceedings, 1879 February-March; 2 duplicate volumes (Box Items 24-25)
  - 8. Contracts, proposals, specifactions, estimates, 1871-1880
    - Proposals, specifications and estimates (Box Boxes 26-32)
      Contracts with principal contractors (Batterson, Upjohn and others); estimates (worksheets); estimates (numbererd series, 20-82).
      Unarranged.
    - Estimates, Fogerty, Batterson (Box Item 33)
    - Estimates, Engineers of Commissioner (Box Item 34)
    - Estimates, Contractors (Box Item 35)
    - Estimates (Box Item 36)
  - 9. Upjohn plans and drawings, 1871-1874; 725.11 fC76up; 12 volumes + oversize items
    These are the completed plans and drawings of the architect, Richard M. Upjohn.
    These volumes are in the classified archives.
    Received at the State Library in 1906.
    - No. 1-58, Grounds, exteriior elevations, north, south, east (Box Volume 1)
    - No. 59-124, Exterior elevations, west & general (Box Volume 2)
    - No. 125-227, Interior elevations, general (Box Volume 3)
    - No. 228-311, Interior elevations, Senate, House, Library (Box Volume 4)
    - No. 312-411, Interior elevations, stairs, foundation, ventilation (Box Volume 5)
    - No. 412-486, Floors (Box Volume 6)
    - No. 487-534, Floors (Box Volume 7)
    - No. 535-569, Tiling & ceiling (Box Volume 8)
    - No. 570-620, Roof (Box Volume 9)
    - No. 659-724, Dome, exterior, interior, ceiling (Box Volume 10)
    - No. 725-806, Detail, stone (Box Volume 11)
    - No. 725-806, Detail, iron, wood, miscellaneous (Box Volume 12)
    - Details of the State Capitol on tracing cloth, 14 items (Box oversize)
      - Foundation plan, 1/8 inch = 1 foot
      - Details of sand stone work, 1/2 inch = 1 foot
      - Stone cutter's details (main stairs), 1/2 inch = 1 foot
      - Details for main entrances (iron gates), 3 inches = 1 foot
      - Mezzanine floor, 1/8 inch = 1 foot
      - Iron details (vault doors, etc.), Full size doors and jambs, 1/2 inch = 1 foot
      - Main stairs, section through G-H, sand stone details #24, 1/2 inch = 1 foot
      - Eastern porch, #26 Elevation, 1/2 inch = 1 foot
      - Footing plan (?), 1/8 inch = 1 foot
      - Sand stone details of main stairs (section), 1/2 inch = 1 foot
      - Drawing to show how to start with marblework of dome above roof, 1 inch = 1 foot
      - Southern porches. Elevation and section, 1/2 inch = 1 foot
      - Tranverse section through Representative Hall, main stairs and library, #10, 1/8 inch = 1 foot
        Encapsulated with drawing listed next.
      - Longitudinal section through library and adjoining towers, #10, 1/8 inch = 1 foot
        Encapsulated with drawing listed above.
    - Specifications for the iron work in the roof and statue for the dome of the Capitol, 6 items (Box oversize)
      Specifications covering the iron work in the roof of the State Capitol, and the one drawing of the top of the dome showing the figure of "Genius of Connecticut", both by the architect Richard. M. Upjohn.
      Presented to the State Library Novembe 26, 1924 by J.J. Connor, Jr. of the Metuchen National Bank, Metuchen, New Jersey.
    - Elevation, sections, plans, and views of capitol parapet, wheel window, and pinnacle, PW-1, 1 item (Box oversize)
    - Elevation and section of dome and laurthorne(?), 1 item; 1/4 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - Design with clock tower, PW-156, 1 item (Box oversize)
    - Second story plan, 1 item; 1 inch = 8 feet (Box oversize)
    - Ground plan, 1 item; 1/8 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - Second story plan, PW-167, 1 item; 1/8 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
      Shows changes to Hall of Representatives proposed by the committee. Proposed by the State House Commission for the Committee of the Legislature, presented to the committee, 1879 February 12.
    - Second story plan, plan no. 1, 1 item; 1/8 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
      Proposed by the committee, 1879 February 12.
    - No. 1340, elevation of one bay of dome, 1 item; 1/2 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - Elevation of one bay of dome, 1 item (Box oversize)
    - Mezzanine story, 1 item; 1 inch = 8 feet (Box oversize)
    - No. 214, roof of Representative Hall, 1 item; 1/2 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - No. 1292, loft plan, 1 item; 1/8 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - No. 1290, section views of dome through parapet looking down on weathering, 1 item (Box oversize)
    - Transverse section through main parts of building, 1 item; 1/4 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - Parapet sections - 4 main towers, 1 item (Box oversize)
      Section views of cornices, columns, windows, rosettes, towers, gables, wheel windows, porches, canopies, and balcony.
    - Elevation of small towers above ornamental band, PW-140, 1 item (Box oversize)
    - No. 1308, sections of tower depicting statues, 1 item (Box oversize)
    - No. 1578, stairwell column views, 1 item; 1/2 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
      Received in Hartford, 1879 February 14.
    - No. 1484, elevation of circular stairs, 1 item; 1/2 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - No. 1216, longitudinal section showing spaces between...showing for light and ventilation of roof, 1 item; 1/8 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - Front elevation of one angle of dome with plan of courses, 1 item (Box oversize)
    - No. 1289, elevation of one bay of dome, 1 item; 1/2 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - No. 1314, section through staircases in dome, 1 item; 1/2 inch = 1 foot (Box oversize)
    - Connecticut State Capitol building plaque layout, 1 item (Box oversize)
  - 10. Descriptions and plans of competing architects other than Upjohn, 1871-1872
    - Ciruclar to prospective architects of the new state capitol building by Connecticut Governor Marshall Jewell, 1871 September 29; copy (Box Box 37, Folder 1)
    - Atwood, Chas. B., 1871-1872 (Folder 2)
    - Batterson & Keller, undated (Folder 3)
    - Billings, H. & J.E., 1872 March 20 (Folder 4)
    - Bryant & Rogers, 1872 January 1 (Folder 5)
    - Emerson & Fehmer, 1872 March 4 (Folder 6)
    - Gambrill & Richardson, 1872 (Folder 7)
    - Hallett, William T., 1872 February 15 (Folder 8)
    - Langerfeldt, T.O., 1872 March (Folder 9)
    - Le Brun, N., 1871-1872 (Folder 10)
    - Peabody & Stearns, undated (Folder 11)
    - Post, Geo. B., 1872 March 6 (Folder 12)
    - Sturgis & Brigham, 1872 March 6 (Folder 13)
  - 11. Time books, 1873-1880; Small books in 2 boxes + 4 larger volumes (Box Boxes 38-39, Items 40-43)
    Time worked records of construction workers and office employees.
  - 12. Materials lists and receipts, 1874-1880 (Box Boxes 44-46)
    Lists of materials ordered, delivered, or received; measurments of pipe, marble, etc.
  - 13. Account books, 1872-1880; 7 volumes (Box Items 47-53)
    Three sets as follows: Volumes 1-5; Volume 6, on earlier and superseded set of accounts; one volume on grading grounds.
  - 14. Vouchers, 1872-1880
    - Lists and copies of vouchers, 1 volume (Box Item 54)
    - 1872-1877 March (Box Box 55)
    - 1877 April-1878 May (Box Box 56)
    - 1878 June-1879 December (Box Box 57)
    - 1880 January-July (Box Box 58)
      Also petty cash vouchers and journals.
    - Vouchers for grading grounds, 1878-1880 (Box Boxes 59-60)
  - 15. Bank books, check stubs, cancelled checks, 1874-1880 (Box Box 61)
  - 16. Miscellaneous records
    - Records, 1871-1880; 1 volume (Box Boxes 62-65)
      Includes bills, invoices, payrolls, a list of sub-contractors' addresses, heating plant layour sketches, expenditure statements, applications for employment, compilations of relevant General Assembly Acts, etc.
    - Account book, 1877-1878; 1 volume (Box Item 66)
    - Detailed estimates for alteraltions to new State Capitol, 1874; 1 volume (Box Item 67)
    - Detailed estimates for alteraltions to new State Capitol, 1874; 1 volume (Box Item 68)
    - Specification book, undated; 1 volume (Box Item 69)